so I'm going to share what I know well
and then talk about how that might
translate and there's going to be a lot
of math here the goal is not to you know
make it so that everything is
completely you're not you won't be
completely proficient in everything if
this is your first time seeing this um
but the goal is that maybe it it
highlights some connections to things
that are important and can give people
people some uh starting points for
further
exploration
so when we talk about these dynamical
processes
the there are a couple of different
things a dynamical process just means
something
changes and a stochastic dynamical
process is one where something changes
in a way that is not uh completely
predictable that there is some element
of
Randomness I'm going to start with
dynamical some examples of dynamical
processes that
are um familiar maybe
so the notation we're going to use is uh
some people really like to use
subscripts
[Music]
for these things and I do not so where
other people might write x sub Z x sub
one x sub 2 dot dot dot I'm am always
going to write it in function
notation which means the same
thing this means X is something I'm
measuring at time at a particular time
um these are equivalent ways they're
just different notations and I prefer
this
one but I want to say that so that if
you look at a different resource and
they use this subscript notation it it's
equivalent
so um I'm going to start with discreet
time because I
think from a from a perceptual
level we experience things typically as
continuous time continuous space but
when we're modeling it often we start
with thinking of it as discreete time
and then we start to think about the
snapshots that we're taking as being
closer and closer and a sort of an
approximation of continuous
time so we're going to have a discret
time and this is going to be a
difference equation which is a special
type of discrete time dynamical system
and I'm going to start there are two
things you need for one of these you
need initial
conditions and you need an update
Rule and this is true you need these two
things no matter what you are working
with whether it's like an L system or a
cellular
automaton or a differential equation you
always will want to have some type of
initial or boundary condition
in an update
rule the initial conditions tell us
where to
start and the update rule tells us from
our current state how do we get to the
next so the example I want to start with
is the the uh dynamical or the
difference equation
specified
by X Sub 0 =
3 that's my initial condition I'm
starting with three of whatever I have
at time
zero and then my update rule will be X
of t + 1 which this is my next next
term will be given by 2
* X of T which is the previous
term or I shouldn't say previous I want
to say now the now
term so I start with three and every
time step I double whatever I currently
have what this
does is I can use this to generate a
sequence of numbers according to this
rule so I would start with X of0 is
equal to 3
now whenever time
ticks my next step X of one will be
[Music]
2 *
3 which is
six my X of
two will be 2 * whatever my pre my now
term is so 2 * X of one
which is
12 and then my x value at time three
will be taking the the value at time two
and multiplying it by
two and I'll get
24 so this process generates a a
sequence of data
that looks like
this and I'm sure you may have seen this
something like this before but I'm
wanting to work from the very beginning
and build up because I just think that
things go more smoothly that
way um are there any questions or
thoughts about what we've said so far in
terms of a a discrete time dynamical
system and in particular having a this
type of discrete time dynamical system
well I hope you're following this okay
and if you're not please feel free to
ask questions or if there's if you're
following it and you think there are
interesting ideas that emerge please
feel free to bring those up as
well so I could look at a similar type
of rule
but instead of always doing exactly the
same thing I could have it where there's
some type of choice that's made
according to a probability
distribution so let's look at the
scenario of the what's called sometimes
the random walk or the sometimes called
the drunkard's walk in older
literature where we have a person who's
standing at zero
initially and then every time step they
flip a
coin and if the if the coin is heads
they move to the right and if the coin
is Tails they move to the left and so we
can track the trajectory of this person
so I'm going to have the
same information I'm going to have an
initial condition um which is I'll start
at xals 0 at time
Z and then I'm going to have my update
rule which tells me how it should change
when the next time step happens
so we're going to go left with
probability 1
12 and we'll go right with
probability so this is now an example of
a
stochastic dis discrete Dynamic discrete
time dynamical system because we have
this additional element of Randomness
that we're not always going to do the
same
thing and now we cannot generate a
single trajectory like we did
before rather instead of um
and instead of a a single trajectory As
Time evolves what we'll have is a
probability
distribution of where this walker might
be
so I'm going to go through this a little
little
thoroughly um when I start
with x of0 equals 0 because my my friend
here is starting on on the number zero
here no problem but now uh when I go to
x of
one I don't know whether they
flipped U left or right so there are two
possibilities in terms of what it could
be this is actually a probability
distribution um or they could be at
positive 1 and the probability that
they're at positive 1 is 1/2
or they could be at negative one and the
probability that they're at negative 1
is2 and sometimes it's helpful to to
draw a tree
here to show okay
the this
um I'll put the probabilities on the
edges
yes I see a hand rais so I'm gonna stop
for a
second sorry I just wanted to know if
your screen went oh okay sorry I had
trouble seeing your screen I was just
trying to move it so I could see it so
sorry to interrupt no no problem I
totally lost I totally lost track of my
own screen for a second
um so I'm going to put probabilities of
zero 0.5 on each of these and then when
I go to x of two it becomes conditional
probabilities because now there's a a
0.5% chance that I move up one and I'm
now at positive two um but there's also
a 0.5 chance if I was at one that I move
backwards to
zero and similarly if I was at negative
one there's a 0.5 probability that I
went forward one to end up at
zero and a 0.5
probability that I went backwards one to
end up at
-2 so now for X of two again it's a a
probability distribution or a random
variable um where there's
a 25 uh 0.25 probability or 25% chance
that I'm at positive2 there's
a 0.5 probability that I'm going to
zero and there is a 0.25 probability
that I'm at
-2 and so what I'm generating here is a
sequence of random
variables where the the next random
variable uh depends on the previous
one but that's the fundamental
difference in a
stochastic difference
equation is that the differences are
random and so I I can't speak to a a
single sequence of numbers or I'm seing
to speaking to a sequence of probability
assignments so I'm going to stop here
for questions because I kind of speed
ran a whole undergraduate lecture there
um but does that make sense and are you
all okay with all this or have questions
about
this I'm tracking and good thank you
cool
so where it
becomes a bit more challenging for me is
to now pass to continuous measurements
rather than discrete
measurements I can do okay when the
difference is allowed to be continuous
so here our
um our update rule was based on a dis a
um discrete random variable
that was only supported on plus or minus
one so if I were writing this as a a
more formal equation like how I wrote
for the first one um I could do that I
could
say x of 0 =
0 and then my update rule X of t +
1 is equal
to X of
[Music]
t
plus b of
T
[Music]
where B of T
equals positive
one with probability 12
and B of
tal1 with probability
one and this would be a way where I'm
taking this B of T random variable which
is just a coin flip and now I'm writing
this in my difference equation
notation
um and I'm I'm putting this B of T
variable for the coin flip other not
notation that we would commonly see
is so alternate notation
here would be to express this in terms
of the
difference so instead of expressing it
this way I could also express it in
terms
of what is the difference between the
next term in the previous term and here
I'm just subtracting this x oft term
over or when we do this often people
will write Delta so another way to write
this is the change at time T is equal
to this coin flip random
variable and so this makes it look more
like a this emphasizes the fact that
there's a difference here because I'm
expressing this in terms of a change
operator
so if the symbols some people symbols
are like no problem for some people
they're a little a little icky but um
that's all they these all mean the same
thing what we could see instead is
instead of the change being expressed as
a coin flip the change could be drawn
from something like a uh a
random so what we had before was
a something where the difference
possibilities we might call it was a
discrete random
variable instead of difference
possibilities just
being1 one we could see something where
the
Walker um takes a
step again still you equ spaced but the
takes a step where the length of that
step
is drawn from something like a normal
distribution
with um let's say mean equals z and
standard deviation equals
one and when we do that it's going to be
it's still going to be possible to do
this type of trajectory generation but
the T they won't look like these
discrete tables we will need to get
into using information about sums of
normal
distributions and we will know that you
know at time time step two our our
possible positions are given by the sum
of the two
um identical independent normal
distributions from the previous two time
steps so it becomes a little bit less
Concrete in terms of just writing these
out
um but
it's it's doable and this would be
something where we're looking at
continuous
time I'm sorry discret time
changes but the possible changes are
coming from a continuous random variable
and then that actually creates our
sequence of random
variables and then this is still just a
sto stochastic difference
equation um where it becomes
a where it becomes a discrete or where
it becomes a stochastic differential
equation is when we shorten the time
steps so that instead of there being so
that we're not thinking about there
being any separation but rather
constantly
the The Walker is constantly making a
decision about whether or not to make a
a very small step and over time those
those instantaneous decisions add up um
I don't have as good of an intuition for
this but the the sort of go-to
example for gaining intuition about
stochastic differential equations would
be to look at something like Brownie and
motion where you have a particle that's
constantly making you know infantes smal
theoretically practically speaking
microscopic random movements and over
time that leads to um the fluctuation in
the market or the the activity of the
gas but the actual prediction of any
single Market history or any single gas
you can only say
probabilistically and the key thing the
key challenge actually is going from
understanding it as a a single time step
single time step single time
step um to instantaneously each of these
changes is happening According to some
random
distribution so that's my best attempt
at giving
some leadup to it for people who haven't
seen it
before I see you say double pendulum is
my go-to would you like to expand on
that sorry I'm trying to unmute myself
not be on video no I mean in terms of
like brownie in motion like I think
think about like a double pendulum also
which is like you can predict the
behavior with some Pro probabilistic
distribution but it's it's like there's
also an element of Randomness it's not
um it's not it's not fully predictable
the way that a single pendulum is so
there's some chaotic movement happening
there like it similar to brownie Brownie
and
motion
um is it still is it stochastic or just
chaotic not
sure because I um I'm saying this as a
general comment it's it's deterministic
so maybe it's not sarcastic
so can I cross it
out yes cross it out yeah because that's
actually something I struggled with a
lot um when I first looked at this was
the difference between chaos and
Randomness and something can be
unpredictable long term because the
complexity of the rules Aggregate and
stack up but it it's actually not random
at all you'll always get the same answer
100 time Steps From Now with probability
one
cool we have an example and a
non-example and both are always really
helpful but again I I wouldn't um I
called my friend who worked in finance
and he gave me some pointers on how to
build intuition on stochastic
differential
equations and we can continue exploring
it but basically I've told you
everything I know about it at this
moment so can you um like just help me a
little bit with the notation in the book
MH um like so I I know like in equation
a46 there's that random term Omega
that's like the um
the the normal distribution maybe like
it helps
to
uh augment the the difference equation
or the stochastic differential equation
um but so that Omega like so that's why
I to think of the double pendulum so I'm
I'm thinking in the wrong place like so
that Omega to me looks like um like an
interval but it's not like so but like
that's why like my intuition is wrong
here you know let me see I'm pulling up
the textbook now
a46 yeah in the appendix yeah so
um it says it's a random term with a
mean of zero so similar to your brownie
and motion
example um but like so for me I that's
why I go to the double pendulum because
I'm locked into that Omega being like
the interval from physics but it's
not yeah it's um yeah what this is doing
is saying like uh the change is the
change at
every you know instantaneous time step
is drawn from
um this normal distribution so instead
of flipping a coin we're we're just
sampling
from like how much the particle could
move left or
right and the the explanation they give
I was kind of trying to follow this
although I used I probably could have
used different notation um but they're
saying if you look at a a discret a
discret difference
equation with
um a discrete time difference equation
where at every time step you pull from a
normal
distribution and
then uh you start to look at the time
steps getting closer and closer and
closer so it becomes instantaneous or
continuous time that that's like the the
actual probably rigorous way this is
defined and that's also helpful
information it as it it says in a rather
understate way the interpretation of
equation a46 is something tricky but
this is saying that when you change
you're going to change and whenever you
change how much you change by is coming
from this this normal distribution with
a mean of zero and uh I'm guessing this
is a standard deviation of
[Music]
something yeah I struggled with that
upside down L term also like what what
does that mean I don't know it's a it's
a GMA um but I don't know what it
represents here unless it's been defined
somewhere it was not defined which is
like something that made me crazy a
little
bit and and then the the TOA is the time
step right like in the in a47 so like
some they flip back and forth between
using uh to as time and T as time so
it's just like a random bug in the
system I think yeah I'm a little bit
obsessive I'm probably going to go and
search for gamma later with copy paste
from this and
see right so so me too and um yeah but
now that like it's great that I uh I
have a much better understanding of the
um well hopefully if you can find gamma
let me know but but already like I know
that I'm I'm on I'm locked into like a
non I'm locked into a deterministic
system in my thought process and it's
not that way so that's that was super
helpful thank you I'm glad it was
helpful and I'm I'm happy to for us to
continue exploring it yeah like when I
did differential equations it was always
um or when I was studying this last time
I studied this it was always in a
deterministic system because we're
trying to predict the outcome so yeah
and my background is into discrete
difference equations coming from um from
either chaotic dynamical system
something like the logistic
equation or um I've done a lot with
computer science algorithm and Analysis
but all of that is also I'm I'm echoing
that I'm also I'm more comfortable with
deterministic and I'm also more
comfortable with discreet time in terms
of my
intuition um Cheryl I see you have a
hand up I believe is that from earlier
or do you do you want to come in
again my apologies no it is from earlier
no worries I'm going to lower your hand
if that's okay please feel free to raise
it again if
yeah cool
um so the other thing
that this is like personal request I
wanted to do this because it helped me
with getting the
definitions um more stable and also
because I am a mathematician if I can
prove something um I want
to and the what I wanted to prove
although proof exist already in the in
the textbook group documentation um was
the equivalence of the different
definitions of variational free energy
and
[Music]
so this will definitely get us into the
weeds it's you know going to be
Technical and
symbolic
um but I I feel it's worth doing so
on page 28 in Chapter 2 equation
2.5 has a couple of different things
that it defines and it just
says these things are
equivalent and whenever I see these
things are equivalent I want to know why
or at least I want verification that
they
are so what we're looking at here is
what's called um variational free
energy this is a function that takes two
arguments the first is Q which is a
probability distribution of some
kind and the second is Y which
is um some data that we
have what's important here is that what
there's just one why like Y is you can
think of it as an observation I believe
is okay and uh this is a single piece of
data I mention that because if that
isn't uh if we don't recognize that Y is
a single thing that we're plugging in
here then some of the calculations
you're like why am I allowed to do that
um and I I'll try to point out where
that fact is
important so for what's going to happen
what we want to show is that couple of
these things are equivalent so one of
them
is that we could Define this
as um negative the expectation according
to Q of x
apologies I have I have somehow lost my
PIN
okay so let me switch back to this uh
screen for a
second so this is what we want to prove
is
that these three different things that
are all present as the
definition um or as representations of
this thing are all actually the
same so I'm going to call the first one
version one second one version two and
the third one version three and the goal
would be to take each of the different
versions and show how we could
manipulate them so they actually look
like the other one so I'm going to start
with version two and show that you can
manipulate it to become like version one
and then I'm going to show version start
with version three and show that you can
manipulate it to become version one and
then that will show that each of these
three things are actually the
same so starting with this definition of
uh starting with version
two if I start start with the cback lebl
Divergence this complexity
term and I say okay I'm starting with d
sub
[Music]
KL Q ofx double line P of
x
minus I'm going to switch back to my
whiteboard and hopefully
the um
hopefully
The annotation will not
[Music]
abandon cool so I'm going to start with
the the version two that we just wrote
this d sub
[Music]
KL Q ofx double line P of
X and then I'm going to take minus the X
expectation over this Q
[Music]
distribution of the natural log
of P of Y given
X and now I'm going to take um I'm just
going to plug in what the definition of
these things is from the actual place
where they were
defined and so the definition of colc
lead
Divergence which I had to look up
because
um this would be the sum over whatever
the possible X's
are of Q
ofx times the natural log
of Q ofx / p
ofx and then so that's this part the
first term the Callback lead were
Divergence and then I'm going to
subtract off the expectation
which is the
sum of Q ofx
times the natural log of P of Y go
X and now I am going
to do um use properties of
logarithms and I'm going to
replace this part with something that it
is equivalent
to so this will become
the sum over x and x of Q
ofx
[Music]
times natural log of Q ofx
minus natural log of p
ofx and then in the interest of space um
I'm also going to replace something here
I'm going to replace the fact I'm going
to replace this probability y given
x with the an equivalent way of
rewriting
it which
is Q ofx
times natural log of
and an equivalent way of writing the
probability of Y giving given X is the
probability of y and x divided by the
probability of
X and now I'm going to use properties of
logarithm again
on this
part and again um the log of a ratio is
equal to the difference of the
logs so
that will become the natural log of P of
YX minus the natural log of P of
X so let's write all this
out I'm going to write them on two
separate
lines because it makes things line up a
little bit nicer so this becomes Q
ofx this first term just stays the same
and then this new term that where I'm
introducing the log
property
becomes natural log
of P The Joint distribution here minus
natural log of P of
X can you see what's going to happen uh
there are a couple of terms that we'll
cancel once we write everything
out so what I'm going to do now is
distribute this through
so this first one becomes I'm going to
take this Q of X and just distribute it
through to the logs and I'm going to
take this Q of X and distribute read it
through to the logs so this becomes the
sum over x and x
of Q ofx natural log of Q
ofx and then I can um split the
summation here so this becomes the sum
of x and
x q ofx natural log P of
X and then if I distribute this minus
and this Q ofx
through this becomes
minus the sum over x and
x q
ofx natural log probability
of y and x and then this minus minus
cancels and I get
plus sum x and x q
ofx natural log P of x
and This this
term is the same as this term just with
signs flip so these
cancel so what I'm left with
here is sum over x and
x of Q ofx natural log Q
ofx minus the sum over x and
x of Q ofx
times the natural log of P probability
of Y and
X it turns out that this is the
definition of
entropy up to a minus with uh multiply
by negative one so this would be the
minus of the entropy of Q
ofx and that this is the expect
ation over the Q ofx
distribution of the natural log of the
probability of
Y so what we did was start with one way
of writing this unpack what all of that
actually was defined to be use some uh
algebra properties of summations and
logs and end up with version one of the
same formula so this shows that version
one and version two as we called it uh
actually do represent the same thing
because they can be one can be
manipulated to be exactly the same as
the
other so version one is equal to version
two I'm not necessarily
expecting um also I made a mistake here
uh this e is not symbol for entropy it's
symbol for
expectation so this should be an
H so here we
have so if you look at equation
2 five I believe it
is says these two things are equal and
now we know for sure that they are and
um if you if you want if it might be a
fun exercise for you
to play with it and
see if you can get the same thing or if
you agree with me but the big value that
this added for me was getting more
comfortable with the
definition any thoughts questions or
comments on that
Zoom here
to get the entire thing on the
board so the
other thing we need to do is start with
version three and end up with version
one
so we're going to start
with thank you for coming and hope you
can come back next
week so we're going to start with
version
three I'm going to write
the starting point which is my version
three
here again starting with the cack Le
blur
[Music]
Divergence and here on minus the natural
law log of the probability of
Y so if I write out what that means I'm
just going to write out the formula
here I'm sorry this is the probability
of x given Y in this
version so this is probability of Ln of
Q ofx / by probability of x given Y and
then this other part doesn't change
so minus the natural log of P of
Y and this
becomes the summation of so I'm going to
do the same thing I did before where I
take this natural log and split it
up and I'm also
um that's probably enough the on still
okay um and it's still minus this
natural Al of P of Y term I'm going to
do the same thing again where I look at
what is the definition of the
probability of x given
Y and I'm going to rewrite the
y as the probability of X and Y / by the
probability of
Y and still minus the probability
natural log of probability
one now we can do the same trick again
where we take the log of the ratios and
turn it into the difference of the
logs so what this becomes is some
Q ofx
of natural log Q ofx
minus natural
log um probability of X and Y and then
because I'm minusing a minus this
becomes plus natural log of P of
Y minus natural log of P of Y now if I
were doing this for a a class I would
have people who wanted to just go ahead
and cancel these two natural log of P of
Y terms and that's not going to work so
what we need to do is take this q ofx
and distribute it through
everything and while we're doing that we
can go ahead and split the sums up so
this is going to be the sum over x and x
of Q ofx natural log Q of
x minus the sum over x and x
of Q
ofx natural log of probability of X and
Y and this equation continues we have
plus the sum over Q
ofx natural log probability of
Y and all of this is minus this natural
log P of Y
term now if we were looking ahead to
think about what we wanted to end up
with we really just want the first two
terms and this sum of our x and x of Q
ofx natural log of P of Y is annoying so
what we can do is Factor this in
front and now I'm going to erase and
rewrite for interest of
space so what this becomes
is natural log of P of
Y times the sum over x and x of Q ofx
because this natural log of P of Y was
just a constant so we canull it in front
and then the key Insight here is that
this n this sum overx and X of Q ofx is
equal to one since Q ofx is a
probability
distribution so I can take the
summation and just turn it into multiply
by one
which means that this term and this term
actually do
cancel so when I take this natural log P
of Y minus natural log of P of
Y I just delete both of those because
they
cancel and here again I'm left with
the negative entropy of Q
ofx minus the expected value
over the Q ofx
distribution of the natural log of P of
XY which is equal to version one of the
variational frey
formula so mathematically all three ways
of writing this are actually the same
and algebraically and you can rewrite
them so that they work out to be
starting with one you can get to the
other and um that's a cool cool thing
that I enjoyed doing but also doing that
helped me internalize and make more
definite some of the definitions of the
formulas and to get an understanding of
things like why is it negative entropy
instead of positive why is it important
it why only be a single
observation there are other other um
versions of the proofs that are well exp
explained that are available in the Koda
so um I'd encourage you to look at those
as well but mainly it's just about I
think the proof is worth doing for
multiple
reasons I do need to go soon or do you
all have any thoughts or questions
before we dismiss and um if you have any
longer thoughts or questions let's
discuss them in Discord and bring them
back to this meeting next
week cool well
thanks for coming out everyone and I'll
see yall uh in a week